good morning john thank you so much for
making time for this this is
really um a great honor for me to to
actually spend time with you and have
this conversation the the last time we
spoke i'll never forget
because it was while i was um at my
grandmother's celebrating
her 103rd birthday and shortly after
your father passed away
and um somehow that
context um really makes it forever
memorable
to me to have a chat with you from from
my grand granny's place
well thank you daniel and and the same
for me i mean i i've uh really admired
the work that you've done
over the years and decades and and feel
sort of
sort of common purpose but also sort of
something else as well
and um i've been looking forward to this
uh conversation so
back to you thank you so much the um
yeah the decades i was just briefly
looking at
your biography on the woolland side
and um you've been
chipping away at this for more than 40
years i
just read that in 1978 you
founded the environmental data service i
i knew about sustainability in 87 but i
didn't know that you already
had founded an organization in 1978
to help people rethink the the value of
nature and
um how important it is for us to uh
fall into life's pattern of creating
conditions conducive to life so
i'm i'm really excited uh to
to also make your work accessible to
people that have
i've built up a following of very
diverse people around the world with the
notion of regenerative cultures but many
people still
get very concerned about big business
and there's this activist energy of all
big businesses other
and i've always loved how you bridged
into the business world and really tried
to work from within
with large corporations um could you
maybe take a little bit of a
time to just give a give a run through
your learnings in those 40 years and how
you've seen
um the issue change and
and how slowly people are seeing the
importance more and more too slowly but
um you must have lived
this waking up in your own life
i think people are waking up and and
it's not just greta thunder but i mean
that she is in a way a symptom of a much
broader
set of dynamics in in our world and i
think at some levels it's immensely
exciting and we may get onto covet 19
and so on the implications of that but
i mean to your question 40 years 45
years professionally but before that
um no we traveled a lot you mentioned my
father he was a
um second world war
fighter pilot he stayed with the air
force we traveled with him so we
lived in places like northern ireland
and cyprus and israel and so on and
um something happened to me when i was
very very young when i was about six or
seven and i was exposed to
in the dark on my own ten tens of
thousands of
baby eels or elves it was one of those
sort of
magical moments where you just suddenly
felt absolutely because i was completely
on on my own in the countryside you felt
absolutely
uh panicked at one level and incredibly
connected
uh at another because i already at six
or seven i
knew about the sargasso sea element of
the
eel's um life cycle and and
and out of that came you know when i was
at school when i was 11
i stood up and that was 1961 and the
world wildlife fund
was just being launched um and i i stood
up in front of 80
fellow students and i was paralytically
shy i didn't
do this sort of thing at all and and um
i asked them for their
weekly allowance for two weeks and got
it from everyone and and
sent that off to the uh one life fund um
and then you mentioned kindly
environmental data services and that was
a lot
later that was in 1978 as you said
but it's interesting that i've founded
ends in environmental data services
with um two people one of whom was max
nicholson who was one of the co-founders
of wwf all those years back and um
and i i discovered you know you you
suddenly find these things about
your own life history and and max and i
were traveling down to
wwf by car in about 1979
and he asked me the question how did you
get involved in all of this
and i said well all i remember was being
at school going into the school library
uh reading something reading a newspaper
i'm just feeling i had to do something
and he said and he said he knew exactly
what that was because they got
i think 10 pages front cover and 10
pages into one of our
major national more popular but national
newspapers
and as soon as he said that i could
remember seeing that coverage in that
paper and subsequently i found the um
the electronic files
uh of all of that but just to conclude
the the first
um organization that i co-founded was
environmental data services
and that wasn't simply to dig back into
the world of the natural
environment and so on it was actually to
dig into the world of business for
for exactly the reasons you've just
described which is that at that time you
know most of my friends
were in friends of the earth or
greenpeace or whatever and they they
didn't like business
to put it mildly i mean they just didn't
trust uh corporate people and and you
know this is after the 60s and and um
all of that sort of cultural
insurrection in a way
but i felt business was crucial i felt
that unless and until we got business
people thinking in the right way
uh a lot of the stuff that we wanted to
see in the world wouldn't
happen that's been a pretty hard slog as
you said but i actually think we've made
a great deal of progress
since how have you seen it changing then
like
because when you founded sustainability
that was a
um shortly before you wrote the book
cannibals were forks and and introduced
a triple bottom line into a lot of
business thinking so so i mean you
personally have certainly
started a rethink in at least
like initially the british kind of
focused business businesses or based
businesses but then
globally um how
how did you because i i sensed that in
germany there was
in the 80s and early 90s there was this
leadership
in in the right direction and then
suddenly in the mid 90s there
was this global globalization
boom where everybody just felt they had
to either rush along with it
or they would get left behind and and i
know that for example in germany a lot
of
companies that were proudly producing in
the region
with regional capacities
maybe exporting key elements globally of
course but
but paying a lot of attention that they
were supporting a community
and where they were based was suddenly
starting to globalize as well and
and exporting manufacturing to other
places
um how did you see that change from
kind of a hopeful start in the late 80s
early 90s to then that backlash
of of greed
i think as long as human beings are
involved you've always got the greed
uh factor and in fact when i went to
university first time around to study
economics and when i gave up economics
after one year in 1968
um two economists lived on with me after
that and both were economists
absolutely loathed to promote by or
hated by my
uh professors and they were nikolai
condratiev and joseph schumpeter and
both of them saying the same thing which
is that
the the economy the the national global
economy it pulses it goes through
periods of um wild excitement
and then wild disillusionment and
despair and then sort of comes out of
the
ashes again and you know schumer to talk
to obviously about creative destruction
and i think we're very much in the
middle of one of those
um periods and these pulses of
globalization
have happened before and they
particularly as you know happened before
the first world war
um that's really interesting okay just
sorry to
come in there the the contractif cycles
um
are normally uh
like you can match them roughly against
major technological innovations
and steam engine and and um
computing internal combustion engine and
so on and so forth
and and
i'm a bit concerned that in this because
you speak a lot particularly now in your
most recent book the green swans of this
massive opportunity for transformative
change
and continuous dynamic improvement
um but then i also saw in a video
in and that volans put out recently
somebody from
from the singularity university driving
this
this agenda of um
it's all about technological change and
my sense is that the next contrative
cycle if there is one
it's actually not a technological um
change
as much as a as a change in in social
technology in governance
in rescaling what we do at what scale
and how we do it
and it's it's a re-jigging of the entire
um economic system
in order to rebuild the redundancies
at local and regional scale that we've
cut
in the rush for efficiency um not
understanding that they're actually
necessary
well but several things can be true at
the same moment
and you know i'm not a technology
fetishist i happen to be fascinated by
science
uh and technology and i do think that we
are
headed into a a another sort of
contratif
up wave if you like and um just as a
context and
the first diagram in in my new book
green swans is
is described as um the u-bend
and i think you know i was talking about
this two and a half years ago and
and the book was completed at the end of
december before covert 19.
but the diagram shows a period of
extraordinary evolution macroeconomic
geopolitical
cultural all the rest of it driven by uh
many of the technologies you've already
mentioned
but i show a a really sort of
catastrophic u-bend uh coming up and
it's not gonna be over in
18 months or two years these things
often when they happen
take 12 to 15 years to clear and when
they do
you look out on a transformed landscape
the economy has moved
and typically it's always moved east you
know it went from china to
india the middle east and it went into
parts of europe then it went into the uk
with the industrial revolution then it
skipped the atlantic to east coast and
the united states and west coast and now
it's going back to china again
um and i think this is this is one of
those
uh moments and and so um people often
challenge
they've challenged me at ends they're
challenging me the sustainability they
challenge me at violence by saying
you seem to like growth and i came up
with the concept of green growth back in
mid-1980s um and the reason i do that is
if you look at a
a forest for example and you have a fire
that sweeps through then you have
regrowth
and it's the same with our economies and
and what goes exponentially done
doesn't come exponentially up but
something else does and i think we've
got to work out how do we
grow that new uh economy
in such a way that we can support if it
gets to 10 billion people
in a way that doesn't wreck the
biosphere
and so on so just very briefly to
technology
the reason why i think we are headed
into a new uh condrative cycle
is that more technologies are now coming
through that
any point in our history as a species so
it's things like
um satellite remote sensing it's drones
it's uh big data machine learning
artificial intelligence
it's the internet of everything it's
synthetic biology
it's robots all of these things too
are starting to come together and they
come binding and hybridizing in ways
that we
uh uh very difficult even for the people
driving those technologies to
envision and and and predict so i think
the next 30 40
years are going to see a convulsive set
of
technology-driven changes whether we
like that or not
and i one of the things i worry about is
that there are many people in the
sustainability world
who are sort of saying you know we don't
want to go there and we don't we are i
don't even want to
believe that's a possibility and then
that set of industrial revolutions
happen
and we're sidelined and then i think we
are set up
to do this sort of whole unintended
consequences
uh game all over again so i'm not saying
that technology is
uh the most important but by god it's
critical and it really does shape our
economies and our societies and in the
end it shapes social media and all the
rest of it shapes the
way that our brains work um sometimes
that's good and sometimes it's a
nightmare
that's that's precisely what i'm a bit
concerned about is
that we yet again haven't really
paused enough despite this current
opportunity to really reflect
um that we've had through covet 19 and
and like i have conversations with
people in in the bay area
and silicon valley that um on the one
hand
would say that they're personally quite
critical with regard to
technology but that they they feel that
exponential tech um is something that
isn't stoppable um but
just as much as we've now seen that we
can take radical decisions like
grounding all airplanes and and pressing
a stop on
on global production um it's
it is possible if we have enough will
and enough conversation
to to have a more nuanced conversation
about
what technologies to use when and how to
use them and
and um at what level of proliferation
and constant turnover because i i don't
see how we have the material and
energetic basis to keep
making more of these um
programmed obsolescence type products
that
that were currently so addicted to and
um i'm also concerned that by having
like i've been in a number of workshops
lately where
when you bring in somebody from google x
to facilitate the workshop
then the entire linguistic framing the
way
we that we think about the solution
space only leads us towards
um technologically based solutions we
never have the conversation
because of the way the workshop is
framed with brilliant minds in the room
there isn't never the opportunity to go
upstream
and say are we doing
things at the right scale how do we
refit human patterns back
into the natural patterns that sustain
life on earth how did how do we
heal in in everything we do this
this false dualism between humanity and
nature the cathedral split that is so
deeply in our narrative
that we now believe that technology is
going to save us
from having destroyed
the capacity of the planet to support
higher life forms if we don't watch out
so
they for me there's a balance between
yes definitely
technological solutions are needed and
it's great that they're there
and we're despite the fact that in the
torah
you have the story of the golem and you
have this faust
and that we've for thousands of years we
knew that
there is a sort of be careful with
technology because you might
what seems like a um servant becomes the
master and then we have become the the
servants of that master
how do you how do you see that nuance
discussion
starting well in in a way let me just
say something and then i'll answer the
question
and and um some of your listeners some
of your viewers may
assume that um i went into business in
the 1970s and i'm part of the business
world and i just wanted to say one thing
which is that
um at different times i've done things
uh
which seemed suicidal or at least
semi-crazy to many people
who were colleagues so for example in
the late
uh late 1980s we launched a campaign
around the concept of green consumerism
we did a book called the green consumer
guide it sold a million copies in
18 months and we were sued
sustainability was sued by
three different business units of one of
our clients which was
uh imperial chemical industries ici
back in the day when it existed and we
were also sued by mcdonald's
and through my life we have periodically
done things which
we've turned down a huge amount of work
uh because it doesn't fit with our
uh values um and and so all i'm saying
is that
greenpeace once described us as sort of
greenpeace and pinstripe
suits in the sense that we were taking
that agenda into
boardrooms and c-suites and so on i just
put that on the table to say
don't make assumptions to the audience
about where we're coming from and
i mentioned my original training as a
city planner
and my thesis though was on urban
regeneration
and that was not just structural and
economic it was also
social and it was environmental uh
regeneration and i
i abs it's wired into the core
of of who i am and the way i think
then let me answer your question which
is um
when i went to uh silicon valley with a
couple of colleagues i didn't know about
four or five years ago i i asked
everyone we met
um the same question and the question
was
have you ever heard of thomas mitchell
jr
and not a single person we met on that
trip had ever heard of thomas mitchell
jr and i would let that say
stage say well perhaps you there's no
reason why you should because he was
then
at his peak in the 1920s and 1930s
brilliant chemical engineer
he had over 100 patents to his name
um and i just very quickly ran through
three stories about
him which one is that he came up with a
brilliant breakthrough technology
which was leaded gasoline
which was a wonderful fuel efficiency
innovation but actually poisoned the
nervous systems of millions of young
people around the world
he then came up with freon sort of
classic chlorofluorocarbons
and blew a hole in the stratospheric
ozone layer
and you know he's been described as the
single organism
in earth's history that has done most
damage to the planet and yet these
entrepreneurs these innovators these
investors
had never heard of him so unintended
consequences was
written in to his dna and then as as
many of your viewers and listeners will
know
he sadly contracted polio in the early
1940s he built himself a semi-robotic
bed to get himself
in and out of bed without nursing care
and it strangled him
and i just i told that story to these
people just say
have you thought about the longer term
unintentional consequences of what
you're doing and the answer was glib it
was
yeah we're thinking about that the whole
time but i then asked and who from the
sustainability world is coming into
challenge at close quarters
the work that you're doing and the
answer was almost nobody
but it's partly because the
sustainability world has largely been
focused on
the industries that caused the problems
last time around so
oil and and coal and automotive and
aerospace and
all that sort of stuff and we're not
looking into synthetic biology we're not
looking at the people who are starting
to think about
how do you start to do deep ocean mining
and things like that i mean
some people clearly are but i think we
that's where i feel we should be leaning
into the future leaning into the future
of technology not because we believe
that technology will ultimately save us
but because unless we're in there
we can't shape the culture that's
exactly the culture you've described
which is
tech rules everything else and and
values
you know sort of we'll discuss that
later no no i i
i completely and utterly um
understand that you are in there to stay
in the conversation in order to
help um to be at the table um
means that you can at least try to shape
the
discourse and at the same time because
like we because of that that respect and
and your
your perspective after 40 years of
knowing industry and what is possible
i'm i'm wanting to test my own
idealism and to somebody else um
against your knowledge of where people
are at and and
business leaders at and because i'm i
sense from because i come come from the
biology end of the spectrum and studying
how
life's dynamics both in evolutionary
terms and but also in terms of
ecosystems health and planetary health
have worked for since the beginning of
life on earth
and i see certain patterns that life
follows
that i feel we've left the path
of like where we are life of course and
to some extent
it's i believe that it is a mental
mistake
to oppose technology and nature in the
senses if technology wasn't
part of the biophysical system that is
actually the biosphere and for
from my definition of nature life is a
planetary process technology is
part of it somehow but it is maladaptive
very often and it is um destroying
fundamental patterns that um that
sustain life on earth
and so if we don't refit our patterns
into those natural patterns using the
best of technology
for me there is like it's it's at the
level of
relocalizing economics relocalizing
governance and relocalizing production
and consumption
and i don't mean village scale cottage
industry i mean
by a regional scale healthy
regional economies that still trade
internationally that still export
but that have
instead of overswinging the pendulum all
the way to only
bigger is better and we just have to
keep growing and
like again the the gentleman from
singularity university in that
video um was sort of speaking the
opportunity of you
calling the exponential 20s and he said
tech is growing exponentially
the grand challenges are growing
exponentially but then he said
the institutions um his name was nick
hahn um
his institution the institutions are
growing and then he spoke of
large corporations gaining market share
and that's still that model of you need
to be one of those
monolithic googles in order to drive
change or a tesla
and and i feel there's such potential
and intelligence and good people in
these networks if they
put their minds to how do we facilitate
creating
true scale linking redundancies
and enable regional production
but we are the intelli like like they
help hold part of the
knowledge exchange and global
collaboration
in order to make this possible for
everyone there's it's a redesign
of of at what scale we do things as well
as
how we use technology no i i totally
agree i mean
as it happens i know nick hahn he came
to my 70th birthday
party last year i i think he's the
gentler end of that singularity
university and exponential
world i think he's well aware of the
grand challenges as they call them that
we now face as a species
and he's trying to position exponential
solutions in a way that will appeal to
corporate people the googles i mean
who helped fund singularity university
of course but um
just a couple of things about your
points around biology and i know i i
admire your
biological roots immensely and i i
i'm going to make it sound as though i i
every subject i take
begin i i i drop out of um
but i when i was at school i gave up
biology or
it was given up for me because i refused
to cut up animals
and um so i i lost that but then
in the 70s and my 20s i came back and
started to write for new scientists one
of our
science magazines and i did that for
five years
and and because of that i got to meet
some of the most extraordinary
scientists and then i edited and as a
hobby in the evenings
a new biotechnology newsletter and i got
to sit
next to nobel prize-winning
molecular biologists as they sort of
docked
proteins on the screen and so on and i
became
very interested in all sorts of
different aspects of biology
including the use of biological
concepts and frameworks in thinking
about our economies and our societies so
for example when i was doing sociology
which is what i went to on to do after
economics
uh first time around was um the work of
e.o wilson at
wilson who who talked about sociobiology
which most sociologists
loathed because it reduced us to the uh
you know the the the status of an animal
and and uh
compared us to you know ant colonies and
so on
i think he was much wiser than that i
think there was
a great deal about what he was um
talking about which we could still learn
from and much more recently i i was on
the board for six years of janine
benius's
biomimicry 3.8 and i i love
some of that biomimicry thinking i you
know i and i it goes back to
some of the reading i did almost a child
people like darcy thompson and so on
on structure and form and and um
just finally i you know i live in london
uh and i you know it's a city and i love
cities and
as a city planner i i learned relatively
early to appreciate both their strengths
and weaknesses
um and now you know cities as incubators
of pandemics
are are sort of back in the news but
london just very recently
declared itself the world's first
national park city
and that for me is the sort of
conceptual approach that you know i
welcome where people start to say
don't think of your city as a city as
you've always thought of it and imagined
it
think of it as an ecosystem and yes it's
got parks it's got green space and it's
got
street trees and all the rest of it but
what can we collectively do
to make it much more of a living
organism that benefits
the health of everyone here and that's
very much more
in people's minds now since kervin 19
hit and they've been able to hear
birdsong and
all the rest of it it's astonishing how
in this country uh
the the uk the interest in wildlife
always high
but just rocketed up uh in in the last
six months or so
you know i felt for me because here in
spain the lockdown was very
intense in terms of we weren't even
allowed out to exercise or
for a short walk so i i literally was
locked into a flat for 51 days with
very little connection to green nature
or the ocean or
the things that nourish me every day
normally and
and i really felt it in my body how
intense it can be when you have
nature deficit disorder like i remember
walking back
um from taking the rubbish out and
the the recycling and um stepping under
a tree
and really noticing that i hadn't stood
under the canopy of a tree for
weeks and it it felt like something was
rushing back into me it was
really quite phytochemical
but in terms of cities
there's of course that's the huge agenda
now how do we deal with our
massive cities and like 19 certainly has
made some people reflect of whether they
want to live in
large cities so there is going to be
some some rearranging happening for at
least the privileged ones that have the
choice to
to decide where to go but even in india
i've
i've heard that a lot of people who were
fleeing into the cities
to find the better life so so to speak
um
are now fleeing back into the world yeah
out of the slums because yeah
the conditions and daniel i i would love
to ask you a question which is you know
i've talked a little bit about
technology a little bit about business a
little bit about
um you know cities and so on but
how do you view the human species how do
you view
the you know people talk about
exosomatic
evolution where where we stop evolving
biologically to
to some degree and we evolve through our
technology and so on how do you think
about that do you think that's stoppable
do you think that's
something that um is a bad thing
and
i personally feel that we have a higher
chance of
a longer and deepening arch of our
evolutionary journey
if we step into the maturity
of um precisely what you were saying
earlier the technology shape
ultimately ends up shaping how we think
i lately
um you know a couple of years ago i was
working with guy education and i was
creating these flash cards that help
people have conversations around
the local implementations of the sdgs
and and while i was working on those i
i used buckminster fuller's advice as my
sort of design briefing of if you want
to change the way people think
don't tell them what to think give them
a tool
the use of which will change the way
they think and i
that giving myself that design brief was
very useful and
very very productive for for that
particular project but lately i've come
back to that sentence
and realized how much maybe also
partially because of my
too much time online too much time in
front of a computer and
feeling that in my own body i began to
realize wait a minute this applies to
every technology
money um computers cars
books exactly and the printing press was
a massive
step in that direction so it changes the
way we think
and yes if we if we
also take gertie's advice that he who
doesn't see nature everywhere sees a
nowhere in the right light
into a deeper dimension we need to
somehow come to peace with technology
being part
of what we do but i but that doesn't
mean that the
adaptive evolutionary path that we now
need to take
to my mind isn't predominantly a
technological one but it's a cultural
one
and biological evolution is too slow
to respond to the converging crises that
we have
um caused by not paying attention to
systemic connections and not
like by the power of science and
technology
came through the reductionist method the
shadows
and it gave us a lot of wonderful things
but the shadow side of that was that it
it compartmentalized
our knowledge and our awareness of the
world in into
silos that now reinforced by
professions and academic disciplines
make it really hard for us to really
think systemically about the mess where
and that's why you're doing such a
brilliant job because you've started so
many different disciplines
um and and and you you're clearly a
generalist
and informed by so many different um and
i
you wilson said that the future will be
the future leaders will have to be
generalists and synthesizers because
because we have a lot of information big
data out there but we have
very little wisdom and for me wisdom
comes through cultural evolution
and wise use of technology can only
happen
if we do it in attunement to the
biophysical realities of the ecosystems
and bioregions we're in so
so for me um
that's part of the evolutionary rite of
passage that our species
is currently going through that that we
have exactly that conversation the
question you asked me is it
to what extent will technology play a
role but how do we
create a culture that uses technology
wisely at the right scale
otherwise i think we will blow it
what's interesting i i would love to be
able to take the lids off
our brains and understand how you and i
both see and the world think about
culture because
when i think about culture um i think
about civilizations
and and their decline and and and fall
uh eventually uh but i also think about
soft and hard culture
and and soft is around who we are and
it's our values and it
it's our interactions and it's our
conversations and so on the hard stuff
is the buildings we build and the way
that they over time start to interact
with
our lives and shape them and it's all
the technologies you use for mobility
and communication and so on
and i you mentioned uh about mr fuller
and and um
it's true that i've given up a fair
number of disciplines along the way but
the one i've always loved uh
is history because i think if you
understand a certain amount about
history you can see a little bit further
into the
future as others have um said and i once
had a
absolutely magical breakfast with um
about mr fuller and reykjavik in the
late 70s
and his capacity to explain
really concepts complex science in a
very i mean for example we were talking
about the oceans at one point and he
said
you take a a a stainless steel sphere
which is
as high as uh i was at the time six foot
he said
and you breathe on it the depth the
condensation of your breath
is the average depth of the you know the
world ocean
and i i found that out of conversations
including this one i learned stuff that
sticks with me
much to a much greater degree than
through
endless classroom uh work or or whatever
although even in classrooms you meet
teachers who are extraordinary
individuals who
who have that capacity i mean i remember
learning spanish to a degree for one
year when i was about
14 and the person who taught me had
fought
on the republican side and the spanish
civil war
he didn't bring very much of that into
the classroom but because he had gone
through that
there was this extraordinary existential
connection
and it had partly to do with history it
had partly to do with the
challenges which in different ways we
all face at different stages in our life
and then that sort of question of what
sort of future are we headed into what's
the future
we uh do we want and i remember having
early 80s
i've been pursuing for years the science
fiction
author frank herbert because he did dune
i'd read that it was a set book when i
was doing sociology religion
at university and i wanted to talk to
him and he lived in
the pacific northwest i have family uh
in seattle and around that area so i'd
often be there and
try and find him and every time i was
there he was somewhere else and finally
we met
in london um a couple of years before he
died
um and he he was just going back to
seattle and then up to
the olympic peninsula and he asked me
where i'd come from and i said i just
come back from
seattle as it happens and and he in dune
as you know he described uh as a
civilization
that built around very very
sophisticated technology to cope with
extreme environmental conditions
and for me when i think of culture i'm
thinking about the fremen culture in in
dune or
or whatever it is and you know he he
turned out to be the most extraordinary
environmentalist
and he described trips that he'd made by
playing down the
west coast of the united states and
seeing the change in the landscape and
the stripping out of the forests and so
on
and he had solar panels even then on his
home and so on his draw
is extraordinarily um i just think we're
blessed to have these people
and we should seek them out wherever we
can find them
absolutely the dedication in the first
book of the dune
trilogy is to all the dry land
ecologists of the
future yeah and that's what the entire
series
is is dedicated to it that there is a
level of
premonition or or clarity about where we
were heading
and like i completely agree i wish i
wish i could practice the voice of the
bene jesuit
um it took me 40 pages to get into that
damn book and then suddenly i was in
that world but it was
it was quite a shock um and that
somebody sent me a
two days ago a video of um
almost a decade-long project in the
yemen
um where they've been bringing back
desertified land which was um
desertified because governments changed
its
policy and controls and they
they're basically trying to sort of you
probably come across the scheme but
harness uh acute rainwater
wall it in have it go back into the
aquifers and now they've got
shrubs and they've got grasses and
they've got trees and so on coming
back and the prospect is the rivers will
come back
as well and this that stuff gives me
chills because that's not only frank
herbert territory
that's the that's the world we've got to
now construct for ourselves
absolutely but that's that's again where
we need to find
that cultural maturity to have the
conversation around
how do we do it because we can reforest
with large corporations coming into the
regenerative space and saying oh yeah
when
we've now found our way and where
monsanto starts large monocultural
reforestation
plantations with um partnerships with
the nature conservancy
so there's strange new bedfellows
happening um
all around the globe and and and yes
maybe we need a little bit of these
uh incremental changes that
that create the enabling conditions for
true transformative change to happen
um but if we don't have a conversation
around how to
like for example it's it's possible to
reframe the entire
climate change problem um as a healing
of the water cycle through
biosequestration
and um geotherapy rather than
geoengineering based uh methods of
going beyond biosequestration or finding
there are few
bio-assisted ways of shifting carbon
from the biological carbon cycle which
is only 300 years
and therefore not long enough to
sequester the amount of carbon we put
out
in the long run we also need ways of
sequestering the carbon into the g
geological carbon cycle which is
much longer and and that would then
enable us to
rebalance um global climate patterns to
a point that
that we don't run over the climate cliff
but but that's precisely where we
it's we have to have this conversation
about scale
um because so many people now say yeah
let's
let's do regenerative let's scale it up
but
regenerative practice is deeply
place based and place sourced it comes
out of
the biocultural uniqueness of
communities and their bioregion or their
their
their life sheds and um
that's where i feel that that if we want
to really be transformative
yes we need to have the conversations
with business but in the sense of saying
did you not see what happens to global
supply lines under covet
19 and and this is still the beginning
of that domino effect that is still
running like i feel a lot of people are
saying when are we coming out and then
they're thinking they can can restart
the the um production but um what's
actually happening is that
upstream in so many not just their
suppliers but the suppliers of their
suppliers
are all so globally interlinked and many
of them have gone bust or
have had different periods of shutdown
and and therefore we we see entire um
areas of business completely unable to
restart
and what we can learn from that is that
we need to
even the big companies need to think
about how do we
decentralize our production and and
there was already a beginning of that
conversation with
decentralized manufacturing and even
large companies started to say okay well
we have one factory in
asia in one factory in north america or
central america
um but my sense is that that
we could take the best of technology and
the best of
co-creative transformative innovation to
actually
reinvent production and consumption in a
way that it
is more biomaterial space that it the
very production
of the materials that we use for the
products we use in the region
actually drive the regeneration of the
local ecosystem because it's
necessary to have more forests because
it's necessary to have healthy rivers
and productive um and
that's where i believe is the fine line
between high technology and the kind of
more permaculture eco
vision of of that future is that because
there's so many of us
we also need to be open enough to say
maybe some of these biomaterials have to
be grown
in test tubes using synthetic biology
but
we have to be careful to do it in a way
that it doesn't um
create unintended side effects and and
again
the the wisdom of
a lot of these elders we mentioned is
that
if we do things at a scale where
feedback is relatively fast
we can of course correct for unintended
consequences much faster
if we create global systems we the the
feedback is too slow
no i agree and i you know as i listen to
you i'm i'm i'm both delighted that
we've got a wider conversation evolving
and
we're having this that discussion now
and for a very particular reason which
is that when i look back at what i've
done
over the years uh part of it has been
i'm a provocative provocateur i mean i'm
i'm basically
allowed into business because they sort
of
either find me and the organizations
i've built interesting and
and and in some ways uh valuable but i'm
i'm
i've been described as grit in the
corporate oyster in a sense that you
know i'm an irritant and and
you know some of these people if they
could throw me out all us out they would
gladly do so but
we're in there to hold people's
attention and also
uh to some degree feet um to the fire
and one of the reasons i've
one of the ways in which i've provoked
is by strapping
unlike concepts together so sort of
oxymorons or whatever but
i i did it with green growth and greek
capitalism back in the 80s
i did with a triple bottom line so you
you take a bit of language that
business people are interested in they
strap something else
it's almost like a trojan horse uh
strategy and we've done it
with social entrepreneurs we've done it
with um
well the subtitle of the new book uh the
coming boom in regenerative capitalism
is partly just to sort of get business
people thinking
what the hell does that mean is there
some way in which
resilience and regeneration do come into
the world of capitalism and markets and
business and
if so how but we all know that every
time you
launch new language it gets used and it
gets abused and people
it's it's they don't always set out to
do the green washing or blue washing or
whatever it happens to be but they
just through wanting to adapt language
to the circumstances in which they find
themselves
they they sort of um make language
uh potentially powerful language uh
quite often
increasingly meaningless and so in
talking about regeneration and
regenerative capitalism
i'm absolutely determined to ensure
that if we can get the attention of the
business community then we can bring the
regeneration
concepts into the boardroom and so on
but do it in the right way
hold ourselves to account to make sure
that uh you know we don't simply give
people new toys to play with
uh but this actually helps drive uh
wheelchair
i i i mean in my book designing
regenerative cultures i also
purposefully um included
what i would consider a paradox into the
title because you don't design cultures
cultures emerge
through the sum total of all the
relationships interactions and
communications that flow among people
and and
our enactment of it constantly and
reenactment of it
um so so you can't really design and
predict them in a sort of engineering
type way
but then we can design for um positive
emergence
and to come back to the subtitle of your
new book and
i think it's it's i i've had a number of
conversation about that subtitle with
people lately
and previously i also had a number of
conversations
similar conversations with people who
had initially supported john fullerton's
white paper development of um which was
in the first
part of the white paper was always
called regenerative um
economics yeah and people and he asked a
white group of people to contribute and
comment on it
and then when it when the final version
of the white paper was um
published it was called regenerative
capitalism and um there was a whole
section of people who were offended by
that and i actually
did i actually said no this is this is
because he's not talking to you your
allies already he's trying to bring this
into a different
arena his former colleagues in on wall
street and in the banking world
and and so it it is actually a powerful
use of language
because he's he's trying to create
engagement through it
but when when i posted recently i thank
you so much for
for the copy and wonderful dedications
really
um means something to me and i recently
posted about
your book and it ensued a whole
i should actually copy it and share it
with you
because people get triggered by the word
capitalism people get triggered by the
word growth
and i i as a biologist agree that it
depends on what kind of growth and it's
not that we like i find it dangerous to
to be devil growth altogether i actually
also personally
feel that to the devil capitalism
and the word capital altogether is is
again
wrong we because it's it's a stock and
flow model
that that is useful to to to work with
but
um but where do you sit with this
because basically there's a lot of
people
trying to redesign or reinvent
capitalism to make capitalism green to
make capitalism regenerative
and then there's a whole other group of
people saying that's the wrong place to
start
because there are fundamental issues
around
um ownership of the means of production
and
and so on that um the capital
capitalism can't be retrofitted we need
to
reinvent a new economic system from from
the bottom up and
where do you sit on on that spectrum
well it's funny i did a
a a webinar yesterday in new york
uh and one of it was around faith and
leadership and
most of the people around the table were
from the business world i mean there was
some
yale professors and so on but um the
whole black lives matter
issue was absolutely the forefront of
people's uh
minds of course and and rightly so
um and one of the things i said part way
through uh
was if you go back into your own family
histories
you'll find all sorts of stuff some of
the stuff you'll be pleased to see and
some of the stuff you really want
so in both my elaine and my wife and
i've been together
for over 50 years now and in both of our
families we've discovered slave trading
it was endemic in in britain and her
family fled to the um caribbean to
barbados
after the english civil war and they got
into sugar production and
slave trafficking one of my
relations i discovered there's a there's
a phrase in english which is when my
ship comes in
and what it means is when my ship comes
in with its cargo i'll pay you off
and this particular person had three
ships coming from africa bearing slaves
and they all sank and he'd signed all
sorts of
guarantees against loans contingent on
the arrival
and sale of those slaves and i say that
because
i think a lot of people who
declare that capitalism is intrinsically
evil or the
the democracy isn't going to work or the
communism isn't going to work or
whatever
start from um a point of view
which is exactly that it's ideological
and there's nothing
extrinsically wrong with ideology as
long as it's properly rooted in
you know our biology and our cultural uh
ecologies and all the rest of it and i
think we look back through history and
we see
every society every civilization divided
against itself
very often brought together against
external threats or whatever but
if we think that we're going to be able
to construct
a and a totally equal totally
sustainable
um economy and society
i i don't believe that i think we can
get close to it but we won't get there
and partly i i was shaped by going out
and working in the early 70s
on alternative technology farms where
people are trying to
model a new way of uh developing and
working very close into nature
and most of those places become became
like lunatic asylums because
you know they were intentional
communities people came with all of
their problems from the
wider world and and um it sort of didn't
work
now i'm
a little bit more confident that we can
take the system that we have and bend it
uh over decades and generations
than i am that we can all suddenly after
covert 19
so to go out and set up our family farms
as a solar roof
and and and create a completely
different economic order i'm i'm
dramatizing for effect but
um i think i think we're very complex
species
i think um environmental crime
not just human rights related crimes are
embedded in our entire history of a
species
and yet and yet and yet along the way
certain communities certain parts of
civilizations have worked out how to
live
much more um in much greater alignment
with
uh natural systems and i think that's
really where we've got to try and
drive the conversation and we've got and
if we leave
capitalists untouched by that
conversation we're going to be swept
aside
i think that is the you know the the
three horizon framework
um yes that in the second horizon where
we're kind of
um as john amazing put it when
hospice working the degenerative
capitalist system
and not out of existence but to to to a
state where we only maintain
what we do want to maintain from it and
we're midwifing a more regenerative
viable system into the world the third
horizon
in that space in between the the second
horizon it's all about dilemma
navigation
um it's solutions are never final
i completely agree with you i think too
many people
somehow when they speak about
sustainability or regeneration or any of
these these visionary goals of we can do
better um they
somehow begin to speak about it as if
there is an end point that if we get all
those pieces in place
then everything will be fine and and
will be
sustainable or regenerative and i
personally believe because the the
system continues to change
it's it's a
journey of learning and apprenticeship
that never ends that we might as well
settle into understanding that it's all
temporary and that that's why in my book
i
do this little bit of epistemological
aikido of
focusing so much on questions rather
than solutions and answers because
we're we're a little bit over um
confident as a species that we can
design
solutions and answers that are final um
when history has always showed us that
the well most well-intended solutions
have turned into tomorrow's problems
so why would we think um that our
solutions would be
differently but but it's it's
in this journey of trying to keep
capitalism
the big money big business engaged
it's such a fine line for me personally
to stay because i always
again bachmann fuller said in the end
only integrity is going to matter
so so i i check in with myself a lot of
what do i do and what do i not do and
for me there is this dance of
engaging business and taking like how
many consultants have i heard
yeah but we can't take our clients that
far they're not ready yet
um this is as far as i can have the
conversation with them
and i i i honor people who are sticking
in that field but
but the minute you do that you're on
that knife's edge between
being the great and the oyster and the
transformative change in the and
the seeding of new thought forms that is
so necessary and
at the same time if it means
incremental solutions then then it
becomes part of what will stefan call
predatory delay like
um and and and yeah it's
i again there's no clear-cut answer to
this we i think we're both
we're all sometimes part of helping a
company
do his their predatory delay game and
and sometimes we
plant a seed that really leadership to
the point that they're really taking the
whole thing in
a whole new direction yeah no it it it
it that's absolutely right
and and i think alex uh stefan with uh
predatory delay has sort of
really spotlighted an instinctive
part of what business does which is to
protect its sunk
capital its you know vested interests
and so on but
just to again to sort of say that in
in a way that we've tried to exactly as
you were saying to
sort of test ourselves against whether
we're really making
the sort of difference that we declare
we want to make um we did a couple of
studies quite some years ago but where
we looked at lobbying activities at a
time when
by companies by at the time when nobody
was talking about that
and when two of our biggest clients uh
asked us to shut that project down we
didn't
um and and uh i'm very pleased that we
didn't and now you've got
people like influence map who are who
are tracking that in much greater
um uh detail we shouldn't be naive uh
the
the and in fact the closer to
transformation we come the more the
entrenched incumbent industries will
fight back
and they won't do it cleanly and they
won't do it transparently they'll do it
behind the scenes in all sorts of
uh different ways so i i mentioned
nikhan came to my
70th it was meant to be a birthday party
it turned into a conference but
um one of the things i said there and
people keep reminding me was
i think you know yes i'm 70 but i think
the next 10 to 15 years are going to be
by far the most
exciting and by far the most challenging
and by far
the most dangerous of my entire working
life
uh to date and i say that because i
think all sorts of things are now coming
to a head and they're starting to feed
off each other so you know wildlife
trafficking leads to
a pandemic leads to a
process of deglobalization for a period
of time that depresses
uh greenhouse gas emissions and so on so
we're living in a system
but without the governance or the
political or the economic systems that
they and
really enable us to do justice to the
system that we've
uh created um and one of the questions
i've been asked
and it goes back to a slightly sensitive
point we've already discussed which
is the role of technology um
i'm i've been wondering whether the
human brain
as it's currently configured you know
the standard issue one that we all have
is really fit for purpose and what comes
next and
if we go on our current development
trajectory and things become more and
more complicated faster and faster and
so on
and the only way i can see of dealing
with that
if that continues is artificial
intelligence artificial wisdom call it
what you will but
uh but at the moment all the signs are
that ai and machine learning are going
off in a
trajectory which will not be uh wildly
helpful
uh on that uh journey so i think
education
is our biggest and most important uh
investment and
we do quite a lot in that uh area and
but it's still one of those
jangling questions in the back of my
mind
that's what we do to failure no i mean
that's a
like you opened up a big box there with
for me ais is something that we have to
be careful with because
um what ai does really well is
integrate quantitative data
and and analyze it and
the problem about how life works is that
life
and the life enabling conditions
at multiple scales are all about
qualitative relationships that
that can be somewhat abstracted into
quantitative
analysis and data but not in their
entirety the it's it's what
maura bateson is trying to bring in with
warm data labs this understanding that
that there's a contextual nuance that is
in the relationship between the
different
siloed data that actually is much richer
but that ai has absolutely zero idea
how to access and and so to get
into a kind of um jack fresno type
um future of um
of having the scientists and the
computer and the big ai
um divi out and and calculate in real
time
global resource flows and then everybody
gets some sort of proportion
i i find that extremely dystopian um
i do too and is a question that we need
to like our
i think our brains might not be able to
cope with the future that we are
heading towards creating with our
technologies but again just as much as
we've designed the economic system and
we can fundamentally redesign it
we've designed those technologies and we
could if there is will
change which technologies we use and how
and and that's exactly where where this
this big question comes in of how do we
address
um like also at your birthday party
nick hurd said the only way that
we um can solve these complex converging
crises is that
if we find a way to break down also the
silos between
the different sectors business
governance and civil society
and because they also make us
like we've created a structural this
functionality and how these three
sectors can pass blame to each other
again because of globalized economic
systems in globalized production it's
even easier to
pass the bug if it is focused on
regional performance into how are we
doing in our region
regenerating social cohesion better
communities better education better
better healthier ecosystems how do we
turn cities
into salutogenic processes like we're
talking cities earlier
patrick geddes over a hundred years ago
reminded us that good city planning has
to be in the context of of the region
he was the first bioregionalist yeah um
before all indigenous cultures which
were all
by the regionals um the
i i think it's education that's why i've
i've put so much effort in my life in
into education because while it's the
slowest it is the highest leverage point
um for for transformative change um
and and i think we opened up
a lot of really flash points where where
i i see the dynamics i see the
development
and there is the sense this is
unstoppable
but i also see
a huge questioning now around the globe
and covet 19 has
accelerated that in black lives matter
now
even through the pandemic yet and now we
have an opening up of
i mean seeing the statue of christopher
columbus being pulled on
somebody could say is vandalism but on
the other
hand it is also an acknowledgement of
that we need to rewrite our history
it is normal no longer good enough to um
to build a story of a nation around
um a a violent um
[Music]
conquest um and celebrated as if it was
the
the greatest um achievement um ever
um so yeah uh
the one thing that i think we're
completely in agree agreement
which makes for a very boring uh viewing
let me let me
let me ask you a question um which is
if you if you thought about having an
absolute blank slate for the next 10
years
knowing what you now know knowing the
people you now know
knowing the scale of the challenge and
the opportunities that we face
what would you do i mean in in a sense
we all do that day to day and
and yesterday we we know we decide how
to sort of invest our time and effort
but
i suppose what lies behind the question
is i mean in a sense you see the
the nature and scale of the challenge
that the species now has to sort of
embrace
whether we talk about growth or
economics or capitalism or whatever and
just incidentally on
john fullerton i mean i i i mean i think
regenerative
economics is a much safer bit of
territory to just
to discuss the future on than than uh um
regenerative capitalism i i've chosen
that phrase simply because it is
slightly provocative it does make people
think and rethink but if if if you
suddenly could do whatever you wanted to
do
what what would it be
um well that's a interesting question
because i'm currently in a
phase where when you earlier i said we
can't all post covert go and
and create our self-sufficiency farm
with our solar panels
um i mean i came from that dream many
many years ago when
in 1999 i moved to southern spain trying
to create
an eco village and environmental
education center
um of showing people how to live the
solutions rather than be part of the
problems that was my
framing back then um by john todd and
all those people
yes um and now i fee
feel like i've spent 10 years um here on
majorca
where i moved because i realized after
years with the ecovillage movement the
transition town movement again still
kind of activist community focused small
scale small is beautiful very
schumacher influenced and working
on these alternative models and
realizing that they they're not at the
scale
where the whole system's design is
actually possible to really be truly
regenerating value flows
both ecological and others and and and
so that's where i i've
come to realize that to refit our
patterns
to natural patterns to my mind is at the
bioregional scale
and and that's why i moved to mallorca
because um
islands are very excellent um
case studies for bioregional change
because the one problem you run into
when you try to do a
sort of thames watershed by a regional
thing is that it's too easy to just
extend the
border into the next watershed if if
something um
isn't available just put a pipe across
the hill
exactly and and so so
uh i personally now feel a real need to
draw back from the advocacy that i've
been doing the last four years since my
book
um has come out and round
my advocacy back into the work
that i've also done for ten years which
is to pull back and nurture
pull together and nurture here on the
island a an ecosystem of collaborators
and and projects
um that that have sprung up some with
a little bit of my contribution others
independently but bringing them together
and making people see that there are
actually already the beginnings of a um
bi-regional regeneration project
happening here and i
am i'm also working with a friend on a
proposal
to plant a million trees on majorca but
not in big plantations but to actually
start a whole new agricultural
and biomaterials research base that
that would benefit all people who live
in any of the four mediterranean climate
zones so entire the entire mediterranean
rim but also california and
south africa and um and australia
to do the research what kind of
very diverse highly productive
local and regional scale planting
systems we can
develop that also look at climate change
coming because
like on majorca we have the opportunity
because we have the four main
mediterranean climate zones
represented on the island because we
have mountains and we have
yeah um different rainfall patterns and
different parts of the island
and and so what what i really want to do
is to
pull back a little bit from the global
and and
a build my own family resilience
um stronger and move into into a
a home that that actually has a bit of
land um
and and practice what i preach in the
small scale there also to have a balance
to
not being on the screen all the time and
then putting a lot of effort into
really working at this complexity of the
bioregional scale to
to create a model that um
that hopefully can inspire people but
with people
like i don't want to be the leader of it
i just want to help seed
and and and work on that and i've been
talking to
to louise about um the possibility of
because
when i first came to majorca i always
had this idea of not doing
workshops but workshops
bringing a small group of people into
the tra montana mountain spending three
or four days
walking together which opens your whole
perceptual fields and brings you into
your body
and then having conversations about how
do we truly work
on becoming leaders for this
transformational change towards
diverse regenerative cultures everywhere
with with people and
and yeah that i think that's where i'm
i'm moving i'm trying to
disentangle myself from all the
the global conversations that are
possible and all the hype and networking
that is going on
at the moment because i i see people
dissipate energy in trying to create the
mega networks and the mega
collaborations and
good practitioners that used to do stuff
in their community on the ground
in their bioregion are suddenly drawn
into this global weaving
um which is important but we need to
find the balance and i want to
try to model that by rebalancing my own
life
that's a wonderful answer and it's made
me reflect
you know i if i had a you know
a a similar blank slate and i'd i i
think i
it would probably go a different
direction from you in the sense that
i love the local uh i you know we've
lived in
this particular house since 1975 and you
know a
lovely community quite a lot of wildlife
around the thames very close
uh by and so on but i think a lot of the
work that i do
has been global i mean or at least it's
been on a global stage
and and in a way my sort of job title
which was sort of
given to me rather than ceased by me
which is chief pollinator
and that ability to link different
things
um that are going in the right direction
around the world i think
will remain uh quite important uh for
the work that um
i do but just on the local level uh
actually links
um i mentioned i think that you know
when i was a child in northern ireland
i had this experience with thousands of
eels and
since that time the population of
european eels has gone down
over 95 percent and the same in the
united states and the same in
uh places like japan and this is a you
know i don't particularly love eels but
i
but there are foundational species for
so many other
uh things that that that have depended
on them and
i don't a few years back um
through an organization called the
sustainable eels group
i was involved in releasing 30 000
elders into the river
seven and it was i was probably the most
magical
moment apart from seeing our daughter's
born or whatever it was actually it was
like giving birth in a weird way because
you know you were giving something to
the
wider world and one of those
extraordinary things that's happened
since then
at that point the the curve was just
coming down and down and down and
just in the last 18 months it started to
come bend
backwards now that's heavy rainfall over
the winter and various other things as
well
but i it was the first very personal
demonstration that i'd had of that on
the bigger scale
sort of eel populations going from for
example europe to the sargasso sea and
back
um that you can have an influence well
we have a malign influence historically
but
you can actually start to bring uh that
back but the implications of that is you
start to have to take apart dams you
have to talk
a lot of the barriers to these um
organisms as they migrate and so on
and just finally i um
we recently launched a sort of an award
scheme there's only three people who've
got it so far and it's called the green
swan
award and and the second person to get
it was sasha bench
and what she's done is to use a um
a paramotor to fly seven thousand
kilometers i think it was from siberia
to the uk alongside buick swans
to just to dramatize to inform
people uh that these things with
migratory
uh roots are and that was over i think
across 11 countries
and along the way hunters were shooting
at them and all sorts of things were
happening with their habitats and so on
and i love these people who are trying
to
underscore spotlight dramatize the
things that are going wrong
and at the same time starting to signal
what we might do
uh differently so um i mean i was born
an optimist but but at times that's
actually rather
uh strained yeah no i i think that
uh einstein again was probably quite
good by saying i'm i'm a pessimist for
the 21st sec
century about an optimist for the 22nd
and so it really depends
it's that cathedral building attitude
that we now need to take to just stay
optimistic that if we do the right thing
over the next century
um the following one might be a lot
easier sailing i don't
i agree with you i think it's a huge
opportunity a massive rite of passage
that we're now
moving through and and and
another answer to your question what
would i do in the next 10 years is
i i've been working with this initiative
that we briefly met at and that started
in 2016 with the commonwealth
secretariat and that's really evolved
into this
um initially the organization common
earth that we launched
officially last october is now about to
be launched the common earth alliance
and the and there are countries like new
zealand
and um costa rica starting a pioneering
of a regenerative developing roadmap
and um at the same time i'm also
closely working with with um villain
favela
and commonland um and and their approach
with the four returns
and and i'm on the advisory council of
the
ecosystems restoration camp movement
that john lew the filmmaker who
was documented large-scale examples of
how we can
bring back bioproductivity into almost
eroded
um dead landscapes
and and i find that in that space there
is such
potential and and um for me
to really be a sensible voice in that
space i need to inform what i say
by locally grounded practice so so
ideally i want to find the balance
between doing my work here on majorca
but
doing it connected to all these people
everywhere who are taking the
re regionalization relocalize as
agenda um seriously and again coming
back to buckminster i agree it's
that the big globalizing system is going
to
have its trajectory but under the radar
we're also building
the the new system that will make the
old system
obsolete and and ultimately that the
result will be a blend between the two
hopefully taking the best
of both worlds it's funny because then
we talked about science fiction earlier
on and i
that reminds me of isaac asimov's
foundation series where you had the
first and second foundation and you had
you know the the conspicuous system
doing what it was doing and then the
psycho historian
harry selden had actually designed
something else that was underneath and
evolving over much longer
time scales and i absolutely agree uh in
in terms of the work that we do i'm i'm
partly trying to say
how can we limit the damage of those
very big dinosaurs as they crash around
the landscape the big corporations
and their supply chains and so on and
how at the same time can we feed
that sort of uh secondary tertiary
growth that's now starting to come
through of people with
much more innovative uh approaches to
all of this and there's something i i'd
love after this to
involve you in which is where we're
launching uh a green swan
observatory just to try and identify
around the world and this is very much
directed to business
and to try and make uh some of the stuff
the good stuff that's happening that is
both uh resilient and regenerative
potentially
much uh more accessible for people
um uh in business and to your point
about the 22nd century
we had a session um just in recent days
with shizenkan
um university which is in centre of
tokyo and yes you know and
and um their business school is um
basically uh positioned as the business
school for the 22nd
century and i think we've just got to
reach out to some of these people who
are trying to
move in similar directions and weave
a a a more energetic set of
communications uh between them all and i
thought that that sense of common
uh purpose which i i very strongly sense
that we share
i have an even stronger sense of that
after this
uh conversation and um you know i i
really would love to
continue this um in in various different
ways so daniel thanks
immensely for the opportunity this was a
wonderful conversation
thank you and also thank you for
doing this work so tirelessly like it's
amazing that you
you still seem so convinced
that this is what you're called to do
and and i mean you
you have every right uh to step back and
say i just want to
do rose gardening now and breed roses or
something and you've done so much of
service but but
i for me it's it's really inspiring
another mentor of mine
um tony hodgson um did his phd with 78
and
is now in his early 80s and is still um
launching
whole new um courses and and active work
and transforming the world and
it just to have this model that
at 70 you still can have the kind of
energy that you
now have to um be of service to the
world
thank you i'd say daniel thank you but i
again
i owe it to uh other models you know my
father who you mentioned kindly earlier
on i mean he died when he was 98
going on 99 and just for most of his
life just continued hammering along and
max nicholson who i mentioned who
co-founded wwf and
several hundred other organizations and
and was a co-founder of environmental
data services
he was still hammering along in his uh
he died when he was 90.
and i just i i don't think there's a
choice i think you know
even if there were not the challenges
that we now face i i would feel
an absolute uh need to do this but
given the urgency and get actually just
the potential of this moment of
history that we now find ourselves in i
just think we can actually have a quite
disproportionately greater
influence collectively now than at any
point in
certainly my working life so um it's all
to play for and it's wonderful to have
allies and colleagues and friends on
that journey so thank you again
immense thank you potentially
potential is the word at the heart of
regeneration unleashing potential
so brilliant thank you my my favorite p
word from now on
okay so say hello to all your team when
you have your stuff
i'll do that daniel in fact i'm just
about to go on a call with them now
yeah okay i'll pass that on bye